

ETH Zurich I Department of Environmental Systems Science

jensdaniel.mueller@usys.ethz.ch

🔏 jens-daniel-mueller.github.io | 🖸 0000-0003-3137-0883 | 🖸 jens-daniel-mueller | 🔰 Jens_D_Mueller

Ocean biogeochemist with a favour for carbon, observations & data science | father of two

About

I'm a biogeochemist studying the ocean carbon cycle through measurements of CO₂ in seawater. Since 2020, I'm working as a PostDoc with Nicolas Gruber at ETH Zurich. We use global ship-based observations to reconstruct the accumulation of CO₂ in the global ocean, and how this drives acidification in the ocean interior. This work profits from the experience gained during my PhD, specifically the development of pH analytics, the analysis of autonomous pCO₂ measurements from a voluntary observing ship and several months spent at sea. As a coordinator of RECCAP2 - the second cycle of the REgional Carbon Cycle Assessment and Processes project - I'm working with an international board of around 100 scientists covering a broad view on the ocean carbon sink through models and surface flux estimates.

Key publications

Müller, J. D. et al.: Decadal Trends in the Oceanic Storage of Anthropogenic Carbon From 1994 to 2014, AGU Advances, https://doi.org/10.1029/2023AV000875, 2023.

Gruber, N. et al.: Trends and variability in the ocean carbon sink, Nature Reviews Earth & Environment, https: //doi.org/10.1038/s43017-022-00381-x, 2023.

Müller, J. D. et al.: Long-term alkalinity trends in the Baltic Sea and their implications for CO₂-induced acidification, Limnology and Oceanography, https://doi.org/10.1002/lno.10349, 2016.

Schneider, B. and Müller, J. D.: Biogeochemical Transformations in the Baltic Sea, Springer International Publishing, Cham, https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-61699-5, 2018.

Müller, J. D. and Rehder, G.: Metrology of pH Measurements in Brackish Waters—Part 2: Experimental Characterization of Purified meta-Cresol Purple for Spectrophotometric pH_T Measurements, Frontiers in Marine Science, https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2018.00177,2018.

Postdoctoral employment

Postdoctoral researcher Zurich, Switzerland

FTH 7URICH

• Environmental Physics | Prof. Dr. Nicolas Gruber

Postdoctoral researcher Warnemünde, Germany

LEIBNIZ-INSTITUTE FOR BALTIC SEA RESEARCH WARNEMÜNDE (IOW)

· Trace gas biogeochemistry | Prof. Dr. Gregor Rehder

Visiting scientist Hamburg, Germany

MAX PLANCK INSTITUTE FOR METEOROLOGY (MPI-M)

• Observations, Analysis and Synthesis | Dr. Peter Landschützer

Education

PhD Chemical Oceanography

Warnemünde, Germany

LEIBNIZ-INSTITUTE FOR BALTIC SEA RESEARCH WARNEMÜNDE (IOW)

07/2014-06/2018

07/2020 - present

07/2018 - 06/2020

07 / 2019 - 06 /2020

- · Ocean Acidification in the Baltic Sea: Involved Processes, Metrology of pH in Brackish Waters, and Calcification under Fluctuating Conditions
- · Grade: With honors (Summa cum laude)

MSc Biological Oceanography

GEOMAR HELMHOLTZ CENTRE FOR OCEAN RESEARCH KIEL

· Grade: 1.2 (ECTS grade, A Excellent)

BSc Chemistry Marburg, Germany PHILLIPS-UNIVERSITY MARBURG 09/2008-08/2009

• Grade: 1.7 (ECTS grade B "Very good")

Experiences

Scientific Employee Kiel, Germany

GEOMAR HELMHOLTZ CENTRE FOR OCEAN RESEARCH KIEL

• Benthic Ecology | Prof. Dr. M. Wahl

Marine Biogeochemistry | Prof. Dr. U. Riebesell

Research Assistant Kiel, Germany

GEOMAR HELMHOLTZ CENTRE FOR OCEAN RESEARCH KIEL

• Evolutionary Ecology of Marine Fishes | Prof. Dr. T. Reusch

Certified Scientific Diver & Divemaster Global

200+ LOGGED DIVES, DIVE MISSION LEADER, NITROX-DIVER

• Off-shore mesocosm experiment, Gran Canaria, Spain (2 months)

• Huinay Scientific Field Station, Patagonia, Chile (3 months)

• Divemaster at Al Dive dive centre, Loubiere, Dominica (3 months)

Research cruises Baltic Sea

10 EXPEDITIONS, 6 MONTHS AT SEA

· RVs Elisabeth Mann Borgese, Aranda, Alkor & Litorina

· VOS Finnmaid

Breaks since PhD

• SVs HRIMFARE & Littorina

Sailor Global

BOAT DRIVER, SAFETY AND RADIO CERTIFICATES

2010 - present • Member of the Academic Sailing Association in Kiel (ASViK e.V.)

· Several sailing campaigns including two ocean crossings

Owner of SV Tina V (2019 - 2022)

CIVIL SERVICE ABROAD (ARCHE, DIJON, FRANCE)

Net academic age and career breaks.

Net academic age (work time since PhD in full-time equivalent)

4 years and 11 months

Kiel, Germany

09/2010 - 08/2012

10/2013 - 03/2014

05 - 08 / 2010

2011 - present

2011 - 2020

Total career breaks applicable to biological age (full-time equivalent)

8 months

07/2005-06/2006

4 years and 2 months

PARENTAL LEAVE (2 MONTHS, 100% WORKLOAD REDUCTION) 07/2019-08/2019

09/2019-10/2019 CHILD CARE (2 MONTHS, 25% WORKLOAD REDUCTION)

PARENTAL LEAVE (2 MONTHS, 100% WORKLOAD REDUCTION)

07/2022-09/2022 PARENTAL LEAVE (3 MONTHS, 33% WORKLOAD REDUCTION)

CHILD CARE (4 MONTHS, 40% WORKLOAD REDUCTION) 03 / 2023 - 06 / 2023

09 / 2023 - 12 / 2023 CHILD CARE (4 MONTHS, 10% WORKLOAD REDUCTION)

Breaks before PhD 3 years and 4 months

DEVELOPMENT COOPERATION (GROWTOGETHER E.V., MONGOLIA) 08/2007-09/2007

03/2008-04/2008 DEVELOPMENT COOPERATION (GROWTOGETHER E.V., GHANA)

BIOLOGICAL STUDIES AS ENTRY REQUIREMENTS FOR MSc in BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY 09/2009-08/2010 LEAD OF OFFSHORE SAILING TRAINING CAMPAIGN (ASV IN KIEL E.V., ATLANTIC OCEAN) 09/2012-08/2013

Publications

PEER REVIEWED

2022.

DeVries, T. et al.: Magnitude, Trends, and Variability of the Global Ocean Carbon Sink From 1985 to 2018, Global Biogeochemical Cycles, https://doi.org/10.1029/2023GB007780, 2023.

Gruber, N. et al.: Trends and variability in the ocean carbon sink, Nature Reviews Earth & Environment, https://doi.org/10.1038/s43017-022-00381-x, 2023.

Kappel, E. et al.: Introduction to Frontiers in Ocean Observing, Oceanography, https://doi.org/10.5670/oceanog. 2023.s1.1, 2023.

Müller, J. D. et al.: Decadal Trends in the Oceanic Storage of Anthropogenic Carbon From 1994 to 2014, AGU Advances, https://doi.org/10.1029/2023AV000875, 2023.

Rodgers, K. B. et al.: Seasonal Variability of the Surface Ocean Carbon Cycle: A Synthesis, Global Biogeochemical Cycles, https://doi.org/10.1029/2023GB007798, 2023.

Yasunaka, S. et al.: An Assessment of CO₂ Uptake in the Arctic Ocean From 1985 to 2018, Global Biogeochemical Cycles, https://doi.org/10.1029/2023GB007806, 2023.

Dai, M. et al.: Carbon Fluxes in the Coastal Ocean: Synthesis, Boundary Processes, and Future Trends, Annual Review of Earth and Planetary Sciences, https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-earth-032320-090746, 2022.

Lauvset, S. K. et al.: GLODAPv2.2022: The latest version of the global interior ocean biogeochemical data product, Earth System Science Data, https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-14-5543-2022, 2022.

Poulter, B. et al.: Inventorying Earth's Land and Ocean Greenhouse Gases, Eos, https://doi.org/10.1029/2022eo179084

Honkanen, M. et al.: The diurnal cycle of pCO_2 in the coastal region of the Baltic Sea, Ocean Science, https://doi.org/10.5194/os-17-1657-2021, 2021.

Jacobs, E. et al.: Upwelling-induced trace gas dynamics in the Baltic Sea inferred from 8 years of autonomous measurements on a ship of opportunity, Biogeosciences, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-18-2679-2021, 2021.

Müller, J. D. et al.: Cyanobacteria net community production in the Baltic Sea as inferred from profiling pCO₂ measurements, Biogeosciences, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-18-4889-2021, 2021.

Sanders, T. et al.: Decoupling salinity and carbonate chemistry: Low calcium ion concentration rather than salinity limits calcification in Baltic Sea mussels, Biogeosciences, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-18-2573-2021, 2021.

Wanninkhof, R. et al.: A Surface Ocean CO_2 Reference Network, SOCONET and Associated Marine Boundary Layer CO_2 Measurements, Frontiers in Marine Science, https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2019.00400, 2019.

Müller, J. D. and Rehder, G.: Metrology of pH Measurements in Brackish Waters—Part 2: Experimental Characterization of Purified meta-Cresol Purple for Spectrophotometric pH_T Measurements, Frontiers in Marine Science, https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2018.00177, 2018.

Müller, J. D. et al.: Metrology for pH Measurements in Brackish Waters—Part 1: Extending Electrochemical pH $_{\rm T}$ Measurements of TRIS Buffers to Salinities 5–20, Frontiers in Marine Science, https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars. 2018.00176, 2018a.

Müller, J. D. et al.: Spectrophotometric pH measurements in the presence of dissolved organic matter and hydrogen sulfide: Perturbations of spec pH measurements, Limnology and Oceanography: Methods, https://doi.org/10.1002/lom3.10227, 2018b.

Staudinger, C. et al.: A versatile optode system for oxygen, carbon dioxide, and pH measurements in seawater with integrated battery and logger: A versatile optode system for O _2 , CO _2 , and pH, Limnology and Oceanography: Methods, https://doi.org/10.1002/lom3.10260, 2018.

Wahl, M. et al.: Macroalgae may mitigate ocean acidification effects on mussel calcification by increasing pH and its fluctuations: Biogenic fluctuations mitigate OA effects, Limnology and Oceanography, https://doi.org/10.1002/lno.10608, 2018.

Fritzsche, E. et al.: Highly sensitive poisoning-resistant optical carbon dioxide sensors for environmental monitoring, Analytical Methods, https://doi.org/10.1039/C6AY02949C, 2017.

Saderne, V. et al.: Intense pCO₂ and [O2] Oscillations in a Mussel-Seagrass Habitat: Implications for Calcification., Biogeosciences Discussions, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-2017-351, 2017.

Müller, J. D. et al.: Long-term alkalinity trends in the Baltic Sea and their implications for CO₂-induced acidification, Limnology and Oceanography, https://doi.org/10.1002/lno.10349, 2016.

Schulz, J. et al.: Aquatische Optische Technologien in Deutschland, Marine Science Reports - Meereswissenschaftliche Berichte, https://doi.org/10.12754/msr-2015-97, 2015.

Wahl, M. et al.: A mesocosm concept for the simulation of near-natural shallow underwater climates: The Kiel Outdoor Benthocosms (KOB): Mesocosms with natural fluctuations and delta treatments, Limnology and Oceanography: Methods, https://doi.org/10.1002/lom3.10055, 2015.

IN REVIEW

Perez, F. F. et al.: An assessment of CO₂ storage and sea-air fluxes for the Atlantic Ocean and Mediterranean Sea between 1985 and 2018, in review, Global Biogeochemical Cycles, 2023.

Resplandy, L. et al.: A Synthesis of Global Coastal Ocean Greenhouse Gas Fluxes, in review, Global Biogeochemical Cycles, https://doi.org/10.22541/essoar.168182303.39621839/v1, 2023.

Terhaar, J. et al.: Assessment of Global Ocean Biogeochemistry Models for Ocean Carbon Sink Estimates in REC-CAP2 and Recommendations for Future Studies, Preprints, https://doi.org/10.22541/essoar.168394734.41886821/v1, 2023.

Воокѕ

Schneider, B. and Müller, J. D.: Biogeochemical Transformations in the Baltic Sea, Springer International Publishing, Cham, https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-61699-5, 2018.

THESIS

Müller, J. D.: Ocean acidification in the Baltic Sea: Involved processes, metrology of pH in brackish waters, and calcification under fluctuating conditions, Dissertation, Universität Rostock, https://doi.org/10.18453/rosdok_id00002303, 2018.

DATASETS

Müller, J. D.: RECCAP2-ocean data collection, https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7990823, 2023.

SELECTED CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

Teaching experience

Global Biogeochemical Cycles and Climate (with Nicolas Gruber & Meike Vogt)

ETH Zurich SS 2022 & SS 2023

Seawater chemistry

- · Circulation of the ocean and atmosphere
- Ocean carbon cycle
- Terrestrial carbon cycle

Analytical and Environmental Chemistry I (with Gregor Rehder)

University of Rostock

LECTURES:

- Dissolved Gases
- Water

Analytical Chemistry IV: Environmental Chemistry (with Gregor Rehder)

University of Rostock

LECTURES:

Dissolved Gases

· Current topic: Baltic Sea Biogeochemistry

WS 2018/19

SS 2019

Funding

SPECTROPHABS BSH

SPECTROPHOTOMETRIC PH-MEASUREMENTS FOR MONITORING OF MARINE ACIDIFICATION IN THE BALTIC SEA

OUTSTANDING PHD THESIS IN WATER CHEMISTRY, SPONSORED BY WALTER-KÖLLE FOUNDATION

co-applicant

Early-Career GrantNational Geographic Society

FINANCIAL AND OUTREACH SUPPORT FOR BLOOMSAIL EXPEDITION

201

German Academic Scholarship

Foundation 2010 - 2018

2019-2022

Multiple fundings granted independently
• PhD scholarship (ideational)

- FIID scriotalship (lucational
- Full student scholarship

Academic Scholarships

- Field work grant, Patagonia, Chile
- Advanced English course, Bath, England
- Summer academy, San Giovanni, Italy

Honors and Awards

Briese Award Shipping company Briese

Outstanding PhD thesis in Marine Research 2019

Dissertation awardGerman Water Chemical Society

Dissertation awardBaltic Sea Research Foundation

Outstanding PhD thesis in Baltic Sea Science 2019

Best poster award

Baltic Sea Science Congress

FOR PRESENTATION BY NEWCOMERS 2017

Book-priceBertha-von-Suttner Gymnasium

FOR EXTRAORDINARY ACHIEVEMENTS DURING THE ABITUR